Market structure is the central concept
at the very core of pretty much every
Financial market and if you're a price
action Trader you need to understand
everything about Market structure
because it directly refers to whether
price is going up down or sideways
without it you'll be continually
battling the market and when you're
fighting against the direction of the
market you're not going to have high win
rates you're going to encounter a lot of
losses and you won't be able to trade
with Clarity so in this class I'm going
to teach you everything that you need to
know about Market structure from the
very basics to some of the more
intricate details that you can use in
your own work so with that said and done
let's get to the learning so what
exactly is Market structure well it
simply refers to the trending direction
of a market and there are three
different Market structure phases that
we need to be aware of there are
uptrends consolidations and downtrends
an uptrend is quite simply when the
market is moving in an upward fashion
and obviously through this phase of
price action we would only want to buy a
downtrend is of course the opposite
where the market is moving down and
through downtrends we are only looking
to sell a consolidation is therefore
just a range where the market is not
doing a whole lot of anything there's no
clear Direction and throughout
consolidation we should just not take
trades unless of course we have systems
that allow us to take advantage of the
liquidity in ranges but for beginner and
amateur Traders I would just focus on
trading with the trend because that's
where the big money's made that's where
the high probability is so to work out
which way the market is going and to
actually give an objetive stance to
identifying uptrends downtrends and
consolidations we use highs and lows an
uptrend is a market where we are
continually forming higher highs and
higher lows so if the market is forming
higher highs and higher lows we know the
market is in an uptrend therefore we
should only look to buy a downtrend is
the opposite it's a market that is
forming lower lows and lower highs so
every low is lower than the previous and
every high is also lower than the
previous now quite obviously then a
consolidation is simply where the market
is trading sideways and not really
providing any Clarity it could be
forming equal lows and equal highs or it
could be forming a higher high followed
by a lower low followed by another
higher high and another lower low
there's no direction in consolidations
therefore they're not the greatest place
to trade every trending move in the
market is made up of two different
primary moves we have impulse moves and
correction moves so an Impulse is the
prot trend movement so here in an
uptrend where we're forming higher highs
and higher lows
the impulses are the movements on the
way to forming new higher highs the
larger moves the reason that the market
is going up a corrective move is then
the small pullback we get because
markets don't move totally linear we're
never going to see a trending Market go
like this there's always going to be
small pullbacks within the price action
which make it more choppy like the one
that I've just covered this is because
we have control from the buyers through
an Impulse move then some buyers will
take profit sellers will start to see
opportunity the market pulls back until
it reaches which is a level where new
buyers are happy to get in and then we
get that next prot Trend movement
because the buyers overtake control from
the sellers and we move into new highs
so that's why that works now what we
want to do when we're trading is look to
capitalize on the inforce moves by
buying in from the bottom of corrective
moves so our job as Traders is to
identify where the correction is and
then use other Concepts to work out
where the correction is going to end and
we'll cover this a little bit later in
the video then we want to buy in from
the bottom of a corrective move so our
Prime buying point would be pretty much
anywhere at the bottom of these higher
lows and then we can take advantage of
the impulse move for either a small
trade or a larger prot Trend trade that
we expect to hold for a longer time span
now for a selling phase in the market
things are pretty much exactly the same
so instead of having higher highs and
lower lows what we would have is a lower
low lower high lower low lower high now
these prot Trend downward movements are
the impulse moves the large moves that
form the reason that the market is going
down so these are the structural moves
that are able to break past the previous
lower lows and leading to continued
downside that is the impulsive move now
the correction or the corrective move is
then going to be the small upward
pullback that forms the lower high in
the market so whichever way we're going
we have impulses as the pro Trend
movements and corrections as these
smaller pullback movements and this
builds the foundation for the work that
you're going to be doing with structure
because we want to work with the trend
if we can use the higher highs higher
lows lower highs and lower lows to
identify which way a Market's going then
we can work out the impulsive and
corrective moves now we have a solid
foundation to start working of to
actually start nailing some great traits
now there's a question I want to answer
before you even start asking it and that
is why should we use raw price action
structure over things like trend lines
if trend lines are easy to identify
because we just connect some highs we
can get that done faster well we're
going to go through a real example here
this is a trend line a downward trend
line so this is supposed to indicate a
downtrend in price so we can see we
connected one high to another and this
is supposed to indicate the trend so the
concept then is every time the market
retests this level it should be moving
into a new selling move and if it
doesn't and it instead breaks upwards
that indicates a change in the trend so
when we see price action like this
occurring where we've broken above the
trend line trend line Traders now see
this as a trend reversal and they will
now look for a pool back and buying
opportunity because they think that the
market has changed Direction which is an
easy mistake to make if you're trusting
in trend lines now I just want to give
you about 5 to 10 seconds to review this
structure if you look at it from a lower
low and lower high perspective has the
structure actually changed like the
trend line suggests well the answer is
no the structure hasn't actually changed
so we have the high here then we had a
break of structure which led us into a
lower low then we had a lower high then
we had had another break of structure
which led us into a lower low then we
had another lower high now we've come
down and formed another lower low if we
take a look at where the price is now
it's below the previous lower high so we
haven't actually changed the structure
at all all that's happened is this
imaginary line that you've drawn on the
chart has broken but in reality the
market is still moving in a clear phase
of lower lows and lower highs so if you
were a trendline buyer and you tried to
buy from here you're going to lose
because the market is still downtrending
and you are therefore battling the trend
now if instead we did manage to get up
and break this high that would validate
a change in the trend and then you could
go ahead and find Opportunities to buy
the other way because the market has
broken out of its lower low lower high
phase and pushed instead into a higher
high and higher low phase but until that
structural point there breaks the real
price structure this trend line means
nothing and this is still a bearish
market now let me highlight what happens
when we focus on trend lines over
structure instead of winning your Buy
trade you are very much likely to lose
because you are fighting the trend so
from a trend line perspective this
looked like a viable buy you would have
lost from a structure perspective what
do we have instead well this formation
of a lower low on this corrective move
could have provided an opportunity for
us to sell when we pair it with some
other Concepts therefore we could have
taken a profitable selling move here so
you could make potentially 3 4 or 5%
while the trend line Trader is losing
now one thing thing that people get
stuck with with structure is looking at
every single little intricate move and
getting confused so we're looking at a
market here which is in a downtrend and
then at the end shifts into an uptrend
we'll go through this as we go along but
what people will do is look at every
single tiny little movement in the
structure and treat that as significant
structural breaks so as you can see I'm
marking the price action up pretty much
from candle to Candle this is how people
look at structure then they get
incredibly confused now that's fine it's
understandable people are going to view
structure this way especially when
you're first getting into the concept
but what I want to do to simplify your
work and this will take some practice
from your side but eventually you'll
start to really understand how to do
this and it will become very very simple
to you is to view structure as waves so
rather than viewing every single candle
Movement we want to kind of zoom out and
get a broad overview of the market so in
this market which we can see is
continually making these lower lows and
lower highs we would identify the
structure in the format of waves so we
have this High we can pull that down to
this low then we have the pull back to
this point then we have a new lower low
then we have a new lower high and then
we have the new lower low all the way
down here we have a lower high and then
we have a new lower low so let me
explain how I've come to the conclusion
here to Mark the structure in this way
we can see this is a clear viable High
then we have a clear viable low low then
we have the pullback forming a lower
high then we come down in this clear
movement and form a lower low then we
have the lower high then we have the
lower low so although there's all this
smaller structure within and this will
become relevant soon don't worry we
don't need to consider every single
small movement as a structural break
because when we look at the higher time
frame picture here it's not these small
movements don't actually change the
larger structure in any way because they
are still confined within the range from
the previous lower high to the previous
lower low so any structure that takes
place here yes can be a valid Trend and
yes can be traded and this is called
substructure which we're going to get
into soon it shouldn't actually affect
your view of the larger Trend because if
we consider this even if this was a
small uptrend it didn't break past the
previous lower high meaning the market
on a big picture perspective is still in
a downtrend so when we can start to view
structure as waves in this manner
instead of pulling ourselves into every
single tiny little movement that forms
in the market structure becomes a lot
clearer and easier to understand and as
I say it's going to take some practice
but you will get used to doing this and
viewing the structure as larger waves
some people nail it right away some
people will find some confusion and but
like all Concepts practice will make you
a lot better so now let's go a little
bit deeper into that concept of
substructure and I'll show you the two
different formats of structure which are
swing structure and substructure and how
we can trade them successfully without
getting confused Market structure is a
fractal concept and that means means the
same price structure movements are going
to occur on a very low time frame and
also on a very high time frame so you
can look at the daily time frame you can
look at the one minute time frame you'll
see these same tendencies in the
structure of the market now because of
this within every larger Trend we also
have smaller Trends and this creates
swing structure and substructure so
let's take a look at this example now
imagine this larger black line which
indicates the swing structure or the
overall higher time frame trend of the
Market is let's say the 4H hour time
frame well then within that every upward
move we have on the 4H hour and every
downward move we have on the 4H hour can
also form hourly 30 minute and 15 minute
Trends within and this actually
continually dials down so then if we
looked within the 30 minute Trend we
would then see smaller 5 minute and
10minute Trends within if we then looked
at the 5 minute Trend there would be
smaller 1 minute and 30C Trends within
that so no matter what time frame you're
looking at there's going to be a smaller
version of new trends inside of that
price action and that is where the
concept of the Swing structure and
substructure comes in so substructure
simply refers to these smaller Trends
happening within the swing structure
movement so if you're a Trader who uses
the daily the 4 Hour and the 1 hour well
then the daily is going to have smaller
4 hour and 1 hour Trends within it and
so on now there's one core way that we
can take advantage of substructure and
the substructure that we ideally want to
be trading is the substructure that
takes place during the corrections or
the corrective moves so remember before
we said the prot trend movements are
impulses the pullback moves are
Corrections when we're trading the prot
trend movements it makes the most sense
to just trade the swing structure trade
the higher time frame move with the
higher time frame Trend but the
pullbacks that we get the corrective
moves actually provide smaller Trends
and generally provide new trading
opportunities that we can capitalize
upon if we understand and use this
concept of substructure so I've marked
out these areas this is ideally where
the substructure will become useful to
you the pullback movements and this is
where the substructure trades become
available so the way that we would do
this is when we're looking at a higher
time frame Trend obviously that's going
to be rather linear just moving to the
upside but if we go to a lower time
frame so now focus on this green line
what we will actually start to see is
smaller Trends and Trend reversals
taking place within and really quick
guys identifying a reversal is rather
simple we are looking for phases in the
market where we shift from higher highs
and higher lows into lower lows and
lower highs this change in the trend
validates a reversal because it tells us
that the market is no longer continuing
with the impulsive pushes to the upside
and is instead now impulsing to the
downside and that's a reversal from a
bullish into a bearish trend so that's
the point where we would stop buying and
instead start to sell now if we were
looking on the other side at the end of
a downtrend to validate a change from
the downtrend into an uptrend we would
look for a break from lower highs into
higher highs and then when the market
forms and validates a higher low that is
where we would look to then start buying
instead of selling now after we see one
of these lower time frame Trend
reversals we would actually see
opportunity to start selling through the
substructure move so if we're following
a 4-Hour uptrend we might find a
30-minute opportunity to sell short term
on the way down towards a more
meaningful area in the swing structure
then we can close our trade and look to
continue with the swing structure once
we start to see the market structure
breaking then if we see the same thing
again again where a lower time frame is
starting to break into a downtrend we
may have an opportunity to trade through
some substructure before the swing
structure movement continues so really
we can have one larger trade working
through the swing structure or a few
trades where we're buying at the lows of
each of the Swing structural movements
but then within that we can also find
conflicting opportunities that will work
for day trades which are going to be
these substructure pullbacks which may
provide lower time frame selling
opportunities for us to take throughout
the day while we wait for the swing
structure to form enough strength for
its next move so now let's take a look
at an example of the swing and
substructure in action now here we are
looking at GBP USD on the 4our time
frame and we can see quite visibly if we
consider the highs and lows we have the
high then we have this low which is
broken structure here making a lower low
then we have a lower high then we came
down and we formed this lower low after
breaking the structure just there so
viewing the structure in waves as we do
we can see we have the high lower low
lower high lower low so we are in a
confirmed downtrend and the swing highs
of the Swing structure points would be
first of all there second of all here so
in order to change the trend Direction
in order to start leading into buys we
would need to see this High break
because we need the market to impulse
into a new trend at the moment the
impulses are pointing to the downside so
there is absolutely no reason why we
should expect the market to do this
until of course and unless of course we
break that structural point now as you
are also going to see though throughout
the corrective moves such as this one
here we have this smaller uptrend so you
can see the opportunities arise Within
These smaller moves now we can actually
buy through corrective movements if we
have the right confirmations to do so
with the understanding and the rule that
we should not look to take price further
than the swing structure high so let's
dial in on this current example here if
we were looking at this trending
structure we have the swing structure
move to the downside but if the market
structure shifted we could potentially
take a buy however any buy that we do
take should only look to lead at a
maximum up to this high and below this
High because at the moment with the
swing structure still pointing to the
downside this high is going to hold
significance and unless this High breaks
we shouldn't look to buy past that point
because it would be unconfirmed and then
we would be fighting the trend so we can
buy into an uptrend if we get one
forming on the lower time frames but at
most we should look to Target kind of
high probability areas below this High
okay now I trade using supply and demand
I'll put a card in the top of the video
breaking down supply and demand if you
want to go and watch a class on that but
supply and demand zones are essentially
just zones where we've seen large
amounts of selling or buying previously
a supply Zone would look like this where
we Mark the last candle before the
impulse down this is an area where lots
of selling took place before so the
concept is when the market gets back to
this point it's likely to start selling
again so what does this do well this
provides us with an idea that this could
act as a magnet for price and this is
where the next movement could come from
so if we were looking to continue the
swing structure our trade idea would be
simple sell from this Supply so when the
market pulls into that area we would
place a sell order with a stop loss
above the high and look to trade into a
new impulsive leg of downward movement
to continue the existing downtrend and
from a swing structure perspective that
means if structure allowed us to on a
lower time frame such as the hourly we
could buy towards that supply and use
that Supply Zone as a Target to then get
out of positions on the buy side and
lead into those positions on the sell
side so providing the market gave us
what we wanted to see in order to
execute a trade here we could buy
through this substructure and that is
what provides these smaller trades so as
we can see now that we're on the hourly
we have indeed actually had a break of
the structure just here so we have this
lower low structure forming and lower
high structure forming on the lower time
frames and then we broke above the
structure just here so what we could do
at this point is look for once again
supply and demand this time I'd be
looking for demand which is the last
candle before this impulsive move to the
upside we would place a buy order just
in this Zone and then we would position
stops below and we would use that higher
time frame Supply as a Target and now
this would become a viable trade for us
to actually take the market higher
before leading into larger shorts so we
formulated two ideas we have the swing
structure move which would be a sell
from this Zone stop losses above looking
to trade into new low price and we have
this smaller idea taking advantage of
this lower time frame structure to buy
through the smaller range targeting this
area remembering that we can only look
to trade within the swing structure
range we can't look to extend this trade
further than that because the impulsive
movements are telling us that the market
is trending down so now if we allow this
Market to play out you see we get the
trade through that substructure before
filling the swing structure trade and
moving to the downside now obviously
this are very loose examples but I'm
presenting you with what you can
actually start to do and a lot of the
trades that I take actually take place
within this substructure and the great
thing about the swing and substructure
style of trading is that you always have
the high time frame picture and the big
picture narrative in mind the higher
time frames are almost always the most
accurate time frames to be trading so
when we build our picture around those
High time frames and then use these
lower time frames to scale into our
positions we have high probability and a
lot of clarity around what the market is
doing before we finish up with today's
class I want to give you a very
important tip and that is validating
reversals with body closures versus
Wicks so before we spoke about how a
shift in the trend or a reversal in the
trend takes place when we shift from
higher highs and higher lows into lower
lows and lower highs or vice versa if
we're going from a downtrend into an
uptrend now one very important thing to
note is that Wicks do not indicate a
break in the trend now we have something
called liquidity and liquidations that
take place in the market if you want to
learn more about liquidity card
somewhere in the top video as well as in
the description for a class on that but
basically not every time that we break a
structural point will the market
continue into reversals sometimes the
market Market will sweep a low as we can
see here and then instead of reversing
actually go back up and make new highs
in the trend now in essence what Wicks
are showing us is a rejection of
momentum so in this selling move we have
this higher low we had a break here
which some people would see as a Breakin
structure and start selling into
thinking this Market is reversing but if
we consider what Wicks show they show
rejected prices so this shows the market
attempted to reverse but failed because
we closed back above in order to to
validate a reversal here we would need
to see candle body closures below this
level if we got a candle body closure
that would tell us the market is
confirming a reversal but this with the
Wix is telling us we are rejecting a
reversal but let's just take a look at
how the market played out here you will
see that instead of moving to the
downside we actually pushed up and made
totally new highs in the trend that's
because we rejected the reversal with
Wix so remember to validate a reversal
you need to see candle body closures Wix
will not cut it because they're actually
showing the opposite they're showing a
rejection of lower prices which is
generally going to lead into just
continuations of further upside so there
you have it there's pretty much
everything you need to know about Market
structure in order to start trading the
concept successfully now if you want to
go deeper into this concept and see how
I build it into a system that
consistently brings me results like this
and has helped people to achieve results
like this Trader who just made $111,000
last week and this other Trader who's
now developed consistency and has made
just over $55,000 in the past 2 and a
half months then I will show you the
systems I use to do that check out the
top Link in the description I'll show
you how I can give you a realistic
outlook on trading and help you to
achieve the full-time career that you're
looking for and if you're not interested
in doing that definitely check out the
video somewhere here on liquidity that
is a really good one to watch following
on from this class that's all from me
thank you for watching I'll see you in
the next video